

Profile

Highly motivated machine learning researcher with a passion for translating machine learning research to the healthcare domain, especially focused on inflammatory skin diseases. Developed SAFARI a framework for sparse biomarker detection for rare diseases. At the moment leveraging genetics in combination with single-cell expression data to identify predictive biomarkers.

Education

PhD Candidate in Computational Biology

Munich, Germany

HELMHOLTZ CENTER MUNICH | TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY MUNICH | LMU MUNICH

Oct 2021 - Present

• Supervised by Dr. Michael Menden & Dr. Natalie Garzorz-Stark.

M. Sc. in Data Engineering & Analytics

Munich, Germany

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF MUNICH

Oct 2018 - Nov 2020

• GPA: 1.7

• Relevant courses: Machine Learning, Machine Learning for Crowd Modeling & Simulation, Information Retrieval, Applied Regression, Foundations of Data Analysis, Foundations of Data Engineering.

B. Sc. in Applied Computer Science

Bayreuth, Germany

University of Bayreuth

Oct 2014 - Oct 2017

• GPA: 2.1

PHD STUDENT

Research Experience

SAFARI - Sparse blomarkers For rARe diseases.

Helmholtz Center Munich

Feb 2021 - Present

- Developed the model agnostic framework SAFARI identitying sparse & robust biomarkers for rare diseases.
- SAFARI works directly on the gene space enabling clinical translation.
- SAFARI ensures high expression levels of genes simplifying their detection in clinical applications.
- Applied to the essential clinical problem of distinguishing cutaneous T Cell lymphoma from eczema, I extracted three potential biomarkers out
 of 20,000 genes from bulk RNA-seq data, empowering early diagnosis and correct treatment.
- Leveraging the three discovered biomarkers I achieve a sensitivity and specificity score of 85% and 93% respectively using a logistic regression model on an imbalanced data set (84:16 class ratio).

Identification of diagnostic markers enabling precision medicine for psoriasis

Helmholtz Center Munich

PhD Student

Apr 2021 - Present

- Developed a linear imputation solution for missing therapy response data of patients, enabling the analysis of complete patient datasets.
- Created an objective metric to assess therapy response, allowing for more accurate in-between patient comparisons and categorization of patients.
- Implemented statistical tests identifying best drug target per endotype.

Leveraging single-cell expression data with genetics to discover predictive biomakers in inflammatory skin diseases

Helmholtz Center Munich

PhD Student

October 2023- Present

- · Leveraging Mendelian Randomization to infer causal associations of cell-type specific gene expression levels and inflammatory skin diseases.
- Implemented pipeline to detect cis eQTLs of single cell expression data from Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells.

Efficient implementation of deep convolutional Gaussian Processes

TU Munich

RESEARCHER

- Jan 2020 Nov 2020
- Implemented deep convolutional Gaussian processes to mimic convolutional neural networks (CNNs) to obtain uncertainty estimations for predictions of the MNIST dataset with the goal of faster computation (see here).
- Conducted a comprehensive evaluation of various imputation algorithms to determine their ability to efficiently approximate the kernel matrix and deliver optimal performance on test data.
- Accomplished a substantial 40% reduction in training time by using only 20% of the original training data while obtaining a high classification accuracy of 86% on the MNIST dataset (98% accuracy using the entire training set).

Apr 2020 - Aug 2020

- Implemented variational autoencoder generating MNIST digits.
- Trained Word2Vec embeddings on a review dataset to showcase embeddings store language characteristics.
- Implemented spectral clustering to users on the social network Yelp. Clustered users based on food preference similarity. Conducted a comprehensive evaluation of minimizing the ratio cut and the normalized cut of the graph regarding how this affects spectral clustering.
- Implemented a graph convolutional neural network performing semi-supervised node classification on the CORA ML citation network. Analyzed how oversmoothing affects the network. Implemented approximate personalized propagation of neural predictions to overcome this problem.

Publications

- Garger, D., Meinel, M., Dietl, T., Hillig, C., Garzorz-Stark, N., Eyerich, K., de Angelis, M., Eyerich, S., Menden M.P. (2023). The impact of the cardiovascular component and somatic mutations on ageing. Aging Cell. https://doi.org/10.1111/acel.13957
- Fischer, F., Doll, A., Uereyener, D., Roenneberg, S., Hillig, C., Weber, L., Hackert, V., Meinel, M., Farnoud, A., Seiringer, P., et al. (2023). Gene expression based molecular test as diagnostic aid for the differential diagnosis of psoriasis and eczema in formalin fixed and paraffin embedded tissue, microbiopsies and tape strips. The Journal of Investigative Dermatology, S0022-202X(23)00156-2. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jid.2023.02.015
- Farnoud, A., Ohnmacht, A. J., Meinel, M., & Menden, M. P. (2022). Can artificial intelligence accelerate preclinical drug discovery and precision medicine?. Expert opinion on drug discovery, 17(7), 661-665. https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/epdf/10.1080/17460441.2022.2090540

Working experience _

Opitz Consulting GmbH

Munich, Germany

SOFTWARE ENGINEER WORKING STUDENT

Oct 2019 - Oct 2020

- Built a docker skeleton for Apache zeppelin, enabling users to start a docker container running Apache zeppelin on openShift with one click.
- Created a web application for Allianz IDS GmbH, allowing employees to track and assign investment orders to respectively responsible colleagues.

REHAU Industries SE & Co. KG

Bayreuth, Germany

SOFTWARE ENGINEER WORKING STUDENT

Feb 2018 - Mar 2019

- Developed ALEXA skills for the 2018 FRONTALE window exhibition, demonstrating several features of the smart window.
- · Implemented a web application for Medi Bayreuth to assess players' fatigue after training sessions and their performance during regular fitness checks to visualize and track their development and prevent injuries.

REHAU Industries SE & Co. KG

Rehau, Germany

SOFTWARE ENGINEER INTERN

Nov 2017 - Jan 2018

· Developed a plugin for the open-source smart home system openHAB, enabling users to connect their automated sensor-based garden watering system with other IoT devices.

Skills

Programming Python, Java, R, SOL, shell

Libraries / Frameworks

NumPy, Pandas, PyTorch, scikit-learn, Spring, scanpy, DESeq2, edgeR

Tools / Platforms

AWS, Docker, Git, LaTeX, slurm

Languages

German, English

Honors & Awards

2023 Poster at ML4H, Accepted Findings Paper at Machine Learning for Health workshop New Orleans, US Inventor, Registered patent "Differential diagnosis of mycosis fungoides, method and system" for 2023

discovered biomarkers to distinguish Eczema from Cutaneous T Cell lymphoma using SAFARI

Munich, Germany

Speaker, Selected Speaker about "Biocomputational analysis of big data" at EADV-ESDR Summer Research 2023 Workshop: Big Data and Translation in Dermatology.

Freiburg, Germany

2023 **Participant**, Selected as participant for summer school OxML - MLxHealth. Oxford, UK

PhD, Selected as a member of Munich School for Data Science (MuDS) 2021

Munich, Germany

Extracurricular Activity _____

TUM MINGA Mentoring Program

Munich, Germany

MENTOR

Oct 2019 - Oct 2020

· Assisted incoming master students from abroad with navigating TU Munich and life in Germany by offering guidance on university procedures, exam preparations, and insights on local resources and cultural differences.

Lern-Fair Munich, Germany

MATH TEACHER Feb 2021 - Jul 2021

• Delivered personalized online math lessons to 9th-grade students during the COVID-19 home-schooling period, promoting understanding and growth in mathematical concepts.

• Developed and curated exercise sheets to reinforce knowledge, deepen understanding, and facilitate independent practice.